How can that be measured? How could we measure it? Fifty years ago, some visionary physicists at Caltech and MIT -- Kip Thorne, Ron Drever, Rai Weiss -- thought they could precisely measure distances using lasers that measured distances between mirrors kilometers apart. It took many years, a lot of work and many scientists to develop the technology and develop the ideas. And 20 years later, almost 30 years ago, they started to build two gravitational wave detectors, two interferometers, in the United States. Each one is four kilometers long; one is in Livingston, Louisiana, in the middle of a beautiful forest, and the other is in Hanford, Washington, in the middle of the desert. The interferometers have lasers that travel from the center through four kilometers in-vacuum, are reflected in mirrors and then they return. We measure the difference in the distances between this arm and this arm. These detectors are very, very, very sensitive; they're the most precise instruments in the world. Why did we make two? It's because the signals that we want to measure come from space, but the mirrors are moving all the time, so in order to distinguish the gravitational wave effects -- which are astrophysical effects and should show up on the two detectors -- we can distinguish them from the local effects, which appear separately, either on one or the other. In September of 2015, we were finishing installing the second-generation technology in the detectors, and we still weren't at the optimal sensitivity that we wanted -- we're still not, even now, two years later -- but we wanted to gather data. We didn't think we'd see anything, but we were getting ready to start collecting a few months' worth of data. And then nature surprised us. On September 14, 2015, we saw, in both detectors, a gravitational wave. In both detectors, we saw a signal with cycles that increased in amplitude and frequency and then go back down. And they were the same in both detectors. They were gravitational waves. And not only that -- in decoding this type of wave, we were able to deduce that they came from black holes fusing together to make one, more than a billion years ago. And that was -- (Applause) that was fantastic. At first, we couldn't believe it. We didn't imagine this would happen until much later; it was a surprise for all of us. It took us months to convince ourselves that it was true, because we didn't want to leave any room for error. But it was true, and to clear up any doubt that the detectors really could measure these things, in December of that same year, we measured another gravitational wave, smaller than the first one. The first gravitational wave produced a difference in the distance of four-thousandths of a proton over four kilometers. Yes, the second detection was smaller, but still very convincing by our standards. Despite the fact that these are space-time waves and not sound waves, we like to put them into loudspeakers and listen to them. We call this "the music of the universe." I'd like you to listen to the first two notes of that music. (Chirping sound) The second, shorter sound was the last fraction of a second of the two black holes which, in that fraction of a second, emitted vast amounts of energy -- so much energy, it was like three Suns converting into energy, following that famous formula, E = mc2. Remember that one? We love this music so much we actually dance to it. I'm going to have you listen again. (Chirping sound) It's the music of the universe! (Applause) People frequently ask me now: "What can gravitational waves be used for? And now that you've discovered them, what else is there left to do?" What can gravitational waves be used for? When they asked Borges, "What is the purpose of poetry?" he, in turn, answered, "What's the purpose of dawn? What's the purpose of caresses? What's the purpose of the smell of coffee?" He answered, "The purpose of poetry is pleasure; it's for emotion, it's for living." And understanding the universe, this human curiosity for knowing how everything works, is similar. Since time immemorial, humanity -- all of us, everyone, as kids -- when we look up at the sky for the first time and see the stars, we wonder, "What are stars?" That curiosity is what makes us human. And that's what we do with science. We like to say that gravitational waves now have a purpose, because we're opening up a new way to explore the universe. Until now, we were able to see the light of the stars via electromagnetic waves. Now we can listen to the sound of the universe, even of things that don't emit light, like gravitational waves. (Applause) Thank you. But are they useful? Can't we derive any technology from gravitational waves? Yes, probably. But it will probably take a lot of time. We've developed the technology to detect them, but in terms of the waves themselves, maybe we'll discover 100 years from now that they are useful. But it takes a lot of time to derive technology from science, and that's not why we do it. All technology is derived from science, but we practice science for the enjoyment. What's left to do? A lot. A lot; this is only the beginning. As we make the detectors more and more sensitive -- and we have lots of work to do there -- not only are we going to see more black holes and be able to catalog how many there are, where they are and how big they are, we'll also be able to see other objects. We'll see neutron stars fuse and turn into black holes. We'll see a black holes being born. We'll be able to see rotating stars in our galaxy produce sinusoidal waves. We'll be able to see explosions of supernovas in our galaxy. We'll be seeing a whole spectrum of new sources. We like to say that we've added a new sense to the human body: now, in addition to seeing, we're able to hear. This is a revolution in astronomy, like when Galileo invented the telescope. It's like when they added sound to silent movies. This is just the beginning. We like to think that the road to science is very long -- very fun, but very long -- and that we, this large, international community of scientists, working from many countries, together as a team, are helping to build that road; that we're shedding light -- sometimes encountering detours -- and building, perhaps, a highway to the universe. Thank you. (Applause)
¿Cómo se puede medir eso? ¿Cómo pudimos medir eso? Hace unos cincuenta años, había unos físicos visionarios en Caltech y MIT, Kip Thorne, Ron Drever, Rai Weiss, que pensaban que se podían medir precisamente distancias usando láseres que midieran distancias entre espejos que estaban a kilómetros de distancia. Tomó muchos años y mucho trabajo y muchos científicos desarrollar la tecnología, desarrollar las ideas, y 20 años después, hace casi 30 años, más de 20, se empezaron a construir dos detectores de ondas gravitacionales, dos interferómetros, en los Estados Unidos, cada uno con cuatro kilómetros de largo. Uno [está] en el estado de Louisiana, en Livingston, Louisiana, en medio de un bosque precioso; el otro, en Hanford, Washington, el estado de Washington, en medio del desierto. En estos interferómetros, tenemos láseres que viajan desde el centro, cuatro kilómetros en vacío, se reflejan en espejos y vuelven, y estamos midiendo la diferencia de distancia entre este brazo y este brazo. Y estos detectores son muy muy muy sensibles, son los instrumentos más precisos del mundo. ¿Por qué hicimos dos? Porque las señales que queremos medir vienen del espacio son las que queremos medir, pero los espejos se están moviendo todo el tiempo, entonces para distinguir efectos ondas gravitacionales, que son efectos astrofísicos y deben aparecer en los dos detectores, podemos distinguirlos de los efectos locales, que aparecen distintos, en uno o en el otro. En septiembre del 2015, estábamos terminando de instalar la segunda generación de tecnología en estos detectores, y todavía no estábamos a la sensibilidad óptima que queremos -- todavía no estamos allí, incluso dos años después, pero ya queríamos tomar datos. No pensábamos que íbamos a ver nada, pero estábamos preparando para empezar a tomar datos por unos meses. Y la naturaleza nos sorprendió. El 14 de septiembre del 2015, vimos en los dos detectores una onda gravitacional. En los dos detectores vimos una señal con unos ciclos que crecían en amplitud de frecuencia después decaían, y eran los mismos en los dos detectores. Eran ondas gravitacionales. Y no solo eso, sino que, descodificando esta forma de onda, podíamos deducir que venían de agujeros negros fusionándose en uno solo, hace más de mil millones de años. Y esto fue -- (Aplausos) Esto fue fantástico. Al principio, no lo podíamos creer. Esto no se suponía que tenía que pasar hasta más adelante. Fue una sorpresa para todos. Nos tomó meses convencernos de que esto era cierto, porque no queríamos dar lugar a ningún error. Pero era cierto, y para despejar toda duda de que realmente los detectores podían medir estas cosas, en diciembre del mismo año, medimos otra onda gravitacional más chiquita que la primera. La primera onda gravitacional produjo una diferencia de distancia de cuatro milésimas de protón. sobre cuatro kilómetros. Sí, la segunda detección fue más chica pero todavía muy convincente para nuestros estándares A pesar de que estas son ondas de espacio-tiempo, no ondas de sonido, a nosotros nos gusta ponerlas en parlantes y escucharlas. Le decimos a esto "la música del universo". Aquí les quiero hacer escuchar las primeras dos notas de esta música. (Silbido) La segunda, la más cortita fue la última fracción de segundo de estos dos agujeros negros, que en esa fracción de segundo emitieron un montón de energía -- tanta energía -- como la de tres soles convirtiéndose en energía siguiendo esa fórmula famosa, E = mc2. ¿Se acuerdan? Esta música, en realidad, a nosotros nos encanta tanto, bailamos con esto, que se la voy a hacer escuchar de nuevo. (Silbido) ¡Es la música del universo! (Aplausos) Frecuentemente la gente me pregunta ahora: ¿Para qué sirven las ondas gravitacionales? Y ahora que ya las descubrieron, ¿qué queda por hacer? ¿Para qué sirven las ondas gravitacionales? Cuando a Borges le preguntaron: "¿Para qué sirve la poesía?" Él a su vez preguntó: "¿Para qué sirve el amanecer? ¿Para qué sirven las caricias? ¿Para qué sirve el olor a café?" Y él se respondió: "La poesía sirve para el placer, para la emoción, para vivir". Y entender el universo, esta curiosidad humana por saber cómo funciona todo es parecido. La humanidad, desde tiempo inmemorial, y todos nosotros, todos ustedes de chicos, cuando se mira el cielo por primera vez y se ven estrellas, uno se pregunta: "¿Qué son las estrellas?" Esa curiosidad es lo que nos hace humanos. Y eso es lo que hacemos con la ciencia. A nosotros nos gusta decir que las ondas gravitacionales ya están sirviendo, porque estamos abriendo una nueva manera de explorar el universo. Hasta ahora, pudimos ver la luz de las estrellas a través de las ondas electromagnéticas. Ahora podemos escuchar el sonido del universo aun de cosas que no emiten luz, como ondas gravitacionales. (Aplausos) (Inglés) Gracias. Pero ¿solo para eso servirán? ¿No se deriva ninguna tecnología de ondas gravitacionales? A lo mejor, sí. Pero va probablemente a tomar mucho tiempo. Hemos desarrollado tecnología para detectarlas, pero las ondas mismas, a lo mejor se descubra de acá a cien años que sirven para algo. Pero toma mucho tiempo derivar tecnología de la ciencia y no es por eso que lo hacemos. Toda tecnología se deriva de la ciencia, pero la ciencia la hacemos para el placer. ¿Qué nos queda por hacer? Muchísimo. Muchísimo. Esto es recién el comienzo. A medida que hacemos los detectores más sensibles -- y nos queda bastante por hacer -- no solo vamos a ver más agujeros negros, vamos a poder hacer un catálogo para saber cuántos hay, dónde están cuán grandes son, sino que también, vamos a ver otros objetos. Vamos a ver la fusión de estrellas de neutrones, que se convierten en un agujero negro. Vamos a ver nacer a un agujero negro. Vamos a poder ver estrellas rotantes en nuestra galaxia produciendo ondas sinusoidales. Vamos a poder ver explosiones de supernovas en nuestra galaxia. Es todo un espectro de nuevas fuentes que vamos a estar viendo. Nos gusta decir que hemos agregado un nuevo sentido al cuerpo humano: ahora, además de ver, podemos escuchar. Esto es una revolución en la astronomía, así como cuando Galileo inventó el telescopio, o como cuando al cine mudo se le agregó el sonido. Esto es apenas el comienzo. Nos gusta pensar que el camino de la ciencia es muy largo -- muy divertido, pero muy largo -- y esta gran comunidad internacional de científicos trabajando en equipo desde muchos países, todos juntos, estamos ayudando a construir este camino, poniendo luces, a veces encontrando desvíos, y construyendo, a lo mejor, una autopista al universo. Gracias. (Aplausos)